{
  "reference_number": "10647",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is important to set a target now and not continue to let this drift into the future. I would prefer that a target of 2040 is set as action is\n\n needed urgently."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "We do need a net zero target overall. And it is vital that we do deal immediately with the long lived gases. I would prefer a combination\n\n that meant that short-lived gases also need to be reduced to sustainable levels and any residual levels are off-set in some way. It is\n not clear that that is the purpose of the second option. Also this needs to happen by 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "International carbon credits are too often open to abuse, and mean that we don't actually take responsibility for reducing our\n emissions directly. Planting trees is important, but we must see that as only a small part of the answer - we must also make\n\n meaningful and sustainable reductions in emissions, i.e. energy, transport, and electricity systems. Planting trees does not actually\n reduce emissions, and if it is to be sustainable, then we must aim for more than just planting trees to absorb increases in carbon\n emissions. We cannot have continued gross emissions growth. We should also not fail to address how we can decrease methane\n\n emissions also."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "1. It should be a 2040 target; and 2. It should only be revised if we can achieve it sooner. It should not be extended out. We simply do\n not have the luxury."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes it helps to forecast."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "We must set ourselves strong and realistic targets. Economic circumstances should be no reason to reduce targets. Perceived\nsavings now will only be increased costs later on. However, targets could be changed only if they were tighter and in the face of\n\ninternational agreement and/or scientific advice."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This MUST mean exceptional and must be within the range. The range must still head in the right direction, there should be no\n'slippage' to targets. If not acting within what was required, i.e. delayed action, then the next 5 year period should anticipate clawing\n\nback any setbacks. Economic reasons are not acceptable, but if there are \"exceptional\" scientific or technical reasons, then that is\nreasonable. Economics of saving now but increased costs later are poor economics. Achieving targets must remain a possibility. And\nexceptions must be exceptional."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, these are reasonable, but the weighting of them must also consider the urgency and importance of the situation and the\n\ndelayed costs that could be forced onto next generations and the environment if action is not taken when the opportunity arises.\nWeighing these matters up should not mean that action is avoided."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, there must be a strict time frame for achieving emissions budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is important to consider the implications for our ecosystems and their ability to maintain life-supporting capacity of our geological\nand biological diversity. Communities must be factored in, and an enabling process to help people adjust - Just Transitions concept. It\n\nshould include ALL emissions, and not unfairly target or avoid certain types, e.g. agricultural. Future generations and their capacity to\nlive with the decisions made today should be at the forefront of issues to be considered. Adaptive measures to assist transition for\n\nbusinesses and communities - play a leading role in this. Commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. Impacts of adjustment should fall\ndisproportionately onto those that can afford it and the industries that contribute the most to the problem"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but that is not quite as strong as it should be. The government can be \"held to account\" to the public by the Climate Change\nCommission, i.e. Government must be legally required to explain its decisions. Also, an additional responsibility for the commission is\n\nthat industries that fail to meet targets should be able to be penalised by the commission, i.e. there could be some sort of\nenforcement role under legislation? To ensure the transparency needed, all reports must be tabled in Parliament, so it is fully\n\ndemocratic and governments can be held accountable for the decision making to achieve progress (or not)."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "As above"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "But also that there should be people who have a strong understanding of the natural environment implications of a warming climate.\nThe natural environment will be the most affected party and has less choices with respect to adaptation, resilience, and both\n\nforeseen and unforeseen impacts, e.g. spread of weed species, large ecosystem collapses, etc. There is too much emphasis on the\nanthropocentric aspects as it is currently structured."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, although it may require additional expertise or sub-committee of the Commission. It should also ensure a proper risk\n\nassessment is undertaken to identify where adaptation may need additional resources and/or support."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The government should prepare a national climate risk assessment and have a national adaptation plan. Government should have\nrequirements on local authorities to achieve targets and adaptations, including district health boards as well as local government. It\n\nshould also look at industry that is critical to achieving targets, e.g. electricity companies, potentially polluting industries, controlling\nenergy emissions - e.g. coal-fired boilers, public transport systems. Therefore I support the use of using reporting powers, and even\n\nimplementing regulations and/or legislation to ensure targets are achieved with respect to adaptation mechanisms. It seems as\nthough the experience of the UK supports this approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes as above. This will better help the country as a whole to progressively implement what is needed with respect to achieving our\noverall targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This Act should also require a 75% majority to make any changes to it by future governments. It should have a target date of 2040,\nnot 2050. The magnitude of the climate change problem is so significant and the science so profoundly in support of urgent action,\n\nthat the earlier target date - with the same target - is a necessity. There is an opportunity here for us to move to a more ecologically\nsustainable society, and we need to move towards that bringing grumpy old systems, industries, and even individuals along with us."
    }
  ]
}
